We're almost there.
Smell the sea.
Sea and that red earth.
Nothing like it.
Excuse me, God.
I don't know what to do.
Should I tell him now? I really think
that waiting this long was a big
I'm engaged to another man and I'm
bringing you home under false pretenses.
That's what it is.
I caught something that... Yeah?
Well, I just thought that you might be a
little bit hungry.
Would you like to pay lunch?
Thank you.
What I wanted to say was that... You're
a town guardian?
Avenue Chronicle?
Oh, the chronicle.
And,
Hattie,
what is it?
Dale? Kennedy destroyed my father.
What?
Worker's housing burned to the ground.
Natalie, next stop. Next stop, Natalie.
Look at this.
Devastation.
I missed you so much, Mother.
Now let her catch your breath.
Now what about Hattie? Where is she?
Good Lord.
Gus.
Gus Pike.
You're alive.
Mr. and Mrs. King.
It is you, isn't it? Of course it's us.
Who else would it be?
Gus has lost his eyesight.
I'm so sorry.
Nobody told us.
It's all right, Mrs. King.
So who else is there?
Fela? No.
Then... Just us.
Good to have you home, son.
We're all standing around here for like
a bunch of niddies.
Now, Alec, where's the carriage?
It's just here.
Among us.
Tell me, tell me.
Olivia and Jasper, are they all okay?
You've got to tell Stuart McCrae at
once.
No, I will. Soon.
No, dear, not soon.
Today. Now.
He has no idea you found Gus.
That is only half of my problem.
Gus knows nothing about Stuart.
trying to tell you something all day,
and I just keep losing my courage.
You're having second thoughts. Oh, no,
no, Gus, it's not that at all.
Every word I said to you in Charleston
was the truth.
Yes?
Well, I didn't tell you everything.
I'd like to sit down.
That's good.
Where I left it.
Gus, when your ship went down, they gave
you up for dead.
And I died right along with you.
For ages, I wandered through this house,
through these rooms, speaking
only when spoken to.
Then one day...
I suppose God took pity on me.
He sent me a friend.
Somebody who brought me back to the land
of the living.
Who's the friend?
Stuart McRae.
You don't know him.
He came to Adam Lee to manage the bank.
We became engaged, Gus.
Do you love him?
It wasn't love.
It was... Oh, I don't know what.
He helped me survive when all I wanted
to do was shrivel
up and die.
You should have told me.
Would you have come home?
No.
That's why I didn't.
Stuart?
Felicity, why didn't you tell me you
were arriving? Let me look at you, my
beautiful girl. Please, let me go.
What is it?
We found Gus.
I brought him home.
We have to talk.
Hello. This is Eddie. Hello. Welcome
home.
Hello, Eddie.
Oh, Montgomery.
Hello, Mr. Baby.
What's this? This is a baby.
I know it's a baby.
Whose is it?
Where did it come from?
Well, there was a young girl at the
cannery, and she ran into some
so she asked us to take care of the baby
for her.
Oh, she's a sweet little thing.
But, good Lord, hadn't you both enough
on your plate to work with a cannery and
all? We have a plan.
Plan?
What plan?
No, no, I understand.
Yes, of course.
You've decided to rebuild immediately.
Is that it?
Well, we have an appointment to see
about the financing with Mr. Stuart
He has some concerns.
Thank you, Stock.
Cries of doom and gloom.
Why, the fate of all Avila depends on
that cannery. And you can tell him I
so. Right.
Yeah.
Truth to tell, Mr.
McRae, see, I have to find some way to
keep the new cannery, see, running all
year round. Canning what?
Well, you see, I'm not quite sure, but
I'll come up with something. You're
putting the cart before the horse,
Jasper, and you know it. Oh, yes, but
is everything, you see. Our workers will
lose faith in us if we don't get going
right away. See, here's the... Here's
the... Here's the...
Good. Tables and chairs and... Yes, and
here we put a nursery so that ladies can
bring their babies to work with them.
What do you think?
It's a fine plan, Mrs. Dale.
But I strongly advise against doing it.
Against rebuilding?
You both want to do the right thing so
badly you're clutching at straws.
Yes, but these people are counting on
us.
And that kind of thinking doesn't hold
up in the modern world.
The most up -to -date cannery money can
buy is already up and running right in
the next town. It's competitive. They've
cornered your suppliers, your markets,
and most of your workers.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, but you see,
that's why we're here.
It's too late.
By the time you're operational, it'll be
a good year.
By then, you'll never catch up.
So you're suggesting we just give up?
I'm a businessman, too.
I'd love to take your loan.
Denying the two of you, you'd pay it
back even if I killed you.
But in good conscience, I can't let you
do it.
You're my friends.
You'd lose every nickel you have.
What about the town? What about me?
Face it.
The other guy beat you to it.
Believe me.
I know how it feels.
Denied your loan?
Not denied.
Exactly advised against it.
Oh, I've lost.
his head, that Stuart McRae.
Still stewing over Felicity, I suppose.
I'll write out a check for you right
now.
How much do you need? We can't take your
money, Hetty.
No, we wouldn't be able to pay you back.
We couldn't live with that.
Yep. You know, we have to cut our losses
right now, not create new ones. You
have to rebuild.
This is our decision, Hetty.
No, no, it is not just your decision.
That cannery is heavenless bread and
butter.
Well, it won't be if we can't compete
with Carmody. Why can't you understand
that? Because I won't allow it. That is
why.
Hedy, we have a family to consider.
A new baby.
Responsibilities. We have to resolve
this in our own way. Oh, you don't have
way. If you do, it's unthinkable.
Please, let's not fight.
Sit, sit.
Sit.
Here we have profiteers sneaking about
our island, stealing away the very heart
of Avonlea with their clever machinery
and their roguish notions of
You choose this moment to turn your back
on us.
This is
my
house.
You get out.
So, how did you pass the time on
Charlton, Gus?
Come with her?
Oh, yes. I'll, uh... I'll get that.
No, I'll get it. No, no, no. Felix, sit
down. Sit down. I'll, uh...
I'll get it. I'll be right back, Gus.
It's him, isn't it?
No, Gus, dear.
He only boards his horse here.
A word with you.
Stuart McCrae.
Why don't you let me take these reins?
So this is Gus Pike.
I never would have come back if I knew
you were engaged.
This is none of your business.
We've made plans.
I've built us a home.
If you're any kind of gentleman, don't
leave.
Hurry up now, girl.
We have a lot to do tomorrow.
Felicity has planned chores for
everyone.
So we have to get a good night's sleep
tonight.
Chocolate!
Can I eat a whole box myself?
Of course you can.
You were so scared you were never coming
back.
There's Mr. McRae.
Did you bring him talking too?
Children, this is Gus Pike.
Gus, meet Callie and Duffy and Edgar and
Balmarie.
They were the first of all our orphans.
Glad to meet you.
All right, first one in bed is the
winner.
Go.
I met him.
Told me he built you a house with his
own hands.
Something I could never do for you.
Don't say that.
You don't understand.
I didn't come back to Avonlea to ruin
everything for you. Oh, God. It's true.
It'll be good to you, Felicity. I don't
need eyes to see that.
There's more to consider than you and
me.
There's your future.
I have to do what's bad.
I have to let you go.
There you go.
Hot coffee.
Felicity said to tell you there's no
point in hiding out here by the
I'm doing what's best.
How about you?
How are things at the hotel?
Oh, the same.
I'm Mr. Tremaine's assistant now.
It's, uh, it's safe.
Oh, safe isn't bad.
No. Just boring.
Albert had this brochure.
Opportunities in Canada for young men.
A whole list of things.
Farming out west, the Navy, mining in
northern Quebec.
I've been thinking about the Navy.
That's what's on your mind.
I haven't told anyone else but you. My
parents will have a fit.
You got enough to eat there?
Good.
How are you fellas doing?
Any word when you'll be starting up?
There's jobs, good jobs in Carmody. Shut
your mouth. Mr.
Dale is doing it best he can.
We've come here to talk to you. Yeah,
talk's cheap. When's the cannery going
It's... It's over.
We've tried every which way to... But we
can't compete with the comedy.
Tanner.
You have been loyal and patient
and...
And I've kept you all waiting much too
long, so... I thank you for
your good years and good work.
Free to go.
I announced it publicly and without my
permission.
Now, Hattie, it's their business, not
yours.
Oh, no, it is not just their business.
What hurts Avonlea hurts me, Rachel,
and... And you can mark my words, those
dales just drove a nail through
Avonlea's coffin.
You did everything humanly possible.
I should have tried harder.
First the Carmody Cannery and then
lightning strikes.
Well, you know, maybe we're looking at
this all wrong. Maybe Providence is
trying to tell us something.
Tell us?
What?
Old Grandpa King used to say, when life
sends you a lemon, make lemonade.
That's all we can do, darling.
Make lemonade.
Thank God for you, Olivia.
What do you say?
Well, it's... Oh, dear God.
There's nothing left.
A few posters all standing there like
blackened scarecrows.
It's enough to make a person weep.
We all have to rise up like a phoenix
from the ashes.
And so must you.
You have talked things through with
Felicity, haven't you?
She's better off with Stuart McRae.
Oh, nonsense.
She didn't travel all that way to
Charleston just to turn back now, you
Neither must you, my boy.
Yet you have to forge ahead.
Oh, I think at another opinion about
those eyes, Dr.
Snow could easily have stopped by the
farm and talked to me.
I don't think so, Miss King.
Sometimes a person loses heart.
Yeah.
But you're not one of those persons,
either.
Courage, that's right.
Take a friend from those who love you.
You'll survive all this.
I promise.
Gus, I'm afraid the news isn't good.
I don't think it will improve.
I've heard about some new operation
they're doing in Charlottetown.
Well, there are new procedures, yes, but
the success rate is low.
Any surgery requiring a general
anesthetic is potentially fatal.
But there is a chance I could see again.
Oh, yes, but there's a greater chance
you could die Or barring that you'd risk
losing what little side you have
Not
fair after all he's been through to be
faced with no choice
at all, but he has a choice
A painful one, yes, but it's a choice
and we'll all stand behind him no matter
what he decides.
Now, what about Stuart?
Have you resolved things with him?
We barely speak.
He's so hurt.
You are going to have to tell him what's
in your heart.
It's the hardest thing you'll ever do,
but...
He'll set you free.
I accepted your proposal in good faith,
Stuart.
Finding Gus changed everything.
You must know that.
I waited a lifetime for you.
I hurt him terribly, Gus.
But I had to end it.
You know, in your worst moments, I've
never known you to have a handkerchief.
Here.
Oh,
it was awful.
I know you're upset, but there's
something I have to tell you.
What?
I'm having the surgery.
Gus, no.
It isn't worth the risk.
It's a chance, Felicity.
Don't try and talk me out of it. I've
made up my mind.
Hologram, Miss King. Thank you.
My dear Felicity, by the time you
receive this, I will be gone.
I'm leaving. I think it is best for both
of us.
I wish you happiness.
To my dying day, I will regret losing
you.
Well, I should be.
Scalpel, please.
Of course I accept the charges, you link
-a -boop.
Sorry for having the sense I can't give
geese.
Felicity!
Lord, he's in the recovery room.
Yes! Yes, yes, we're here!
Yes!
through it with flying colors.
Oh, Felicity, thank goodness.
What about his sight?
It's too soon to tell. We'll keep him
sedated so he doesn't move his head too
much, and then we'll just have to wait
and see.
Well...
Felicity,
you go and have a rest, dear. I'll stay
here.
Fine, I'll go get us some tea.
I'm right here, Gus.
I always will be.
You're my whole life.
I've never been anyone else.
Remember?
You came running into the classroom,
barefoot, smoking that awful pipe.
I fell in love with that boy.
And when this is all over,
Whether you can see or not, I will marry
you as I should have when you first
proposed to me.
That's a proposal.
I accept.
I can still now.
Don't open your eyes until I tell you.
All right.
Slowly now.
could sign just by give it time
doctor says that with corrective lenses
you should see some improvement
i'm just really hopeful that i'll get a
bit better every day
this king says he'll be going on a
honeymoon
maybe a way long nope when we come back
here though We thought maybe we'd take a
stab at living with you and the other
kids at the Fowling Home.
Yeah!
Gus Pike, you're recovering from
surgery. You're supposed to be resting.
Oh,
Jennifer, there's no way to plan a
wedding. Well, for one thing, it ought
at the hotel.
How can you cram that many people into
the church? It's all too hodgepodge for
my taste.
Oh, two, if you'd just postpone it a few
more days, then Sarah might get here.
Well, I've cabled her, provided there's
time for her to book passage on a ship.
Oh, I have no faith in schemeships.
Floundering about the stormy sea like
great puffing elephants.
I tremble for the child's safety.
She'll be fine.
But Olivia's late. I wonder why she
called this meeting of the clan.
Good night, my love.
You're absolutely sure?
Of course I'm sure.
We have one life to live.
What life?
Life.
We've decided to leave Avonlea.
Jasper has been offered and has now
accepted a permanent position with the
Society. Oh, wonderful, wonderful.
Leave, haven't they?
You can't.
Well, we're doing it, Hetty.
That's why I'm asking for my share of
the family trust.
Yes, well, you can't have it.
I'll not see the king principal divided
for such arrant selfishness.
Now, just hold on. Oh, really, Hedy?
There's more than one person. No, no. I
said no.
She'll get that money over my dead body,
and that's final.
Hedy, you have no right.
Right, right. Who cares about rights?
Well, what about duty and obligation?
Heavenly needs you. How dare you desert
us now that the chips are down. You,
you and that nitwit husband of yours.
That's enough, Hedy.
Jasper, I'm sorry. She... We've decided
to leave Avonlea with her without your
money.
Where is your backbone, girl?
Hmm? You're your sense of community.
Oh, we kings.
Set an example here.
Oh, if you run, everyone will run.
Stop trying to make her feel like
Ingrid.
Hattie, I'm sick to death of you
continually trying to rule the roost.
own the trust alone.
Hattie, Janet is right.
The trust isn't yours alone.
Two out of three wins.
I'm one voter.
Alec?
Alec can do today.
I vote that Olivia takes her share of
the trust.
That's the way it is.
Betrayed by my own family.
Judas is the lot of you.
Women.
Please don't do this. Not with the
wedding so soon.
Wedding? Why would I come to a wedding
where I'm not wanted?
No one said that. Oh, yes, but actually,
louder than words. No, no, I do not set
foot at a wedding with a pack of
traitors.
Not if you pick me on bended knee.
Eddie King, you will live to regret
this.
I'll come back for Felicity.
Good Lord.
I joined up.
I guess rebel blood runs in the family.
Thank you.
King, you're not even... Don't go. Just
a moment. We're going to the church.
Heather, I'm not going.
What are you talking about?
There's no time now for that.
Suffice it to say that this family has
chosen to side with the profit mongers
and I'll not condone it.
Olivia's leaving and Alex supports...
Stop this.
It seems to me you've... painted
yourself into a cornrow.
You change your mind this minute and
come with me.
No. No, you go, child. And with my
blessing, go on.
But I'll not be there.
How you feeling, old man?
Um, a bit warm.
Find it hot in here?
Not at all.
Said you had the ring right here in my
pocket.
You'll be all right guys Just a bit
nervous I'm doing right by
yourself there, but you will Got a case
of the jitters myself, but going to see
I mean Don't worry.
I'll make a fine sailor Felix. Okay, I'm
half as good as you are.
I Always looked up to you cuss
I'm looking up to you.
I'm glad you're done enough.
I never had a brother before.
Felicity!
Oh, you take my breath away. Thank you,
Miss Livia.
You don't look so bad either, father of
the bride. Thank you.
She's not here. I feel like it's all my
fault.
Don't blame yourself, Olivia. Nothing
will change that old bird's mind.
Sarah!
Listening. Oh, Sarah, you made it.
I wouldn't miss your wedding for
anything in the world.
Look at you.
You're wicked.
Come here.
Sarah, have you seen Aunt Hattie?
Sarah, Felicity.
She's impossible.
She'll be here.
I know she will.
If either of you know any impediment why
you may not be joined in matrimony, let
you confess it now.
Everyone, stay where you are.
I refuse to get married without you. No.
It's my day and I'll do the talking.
Show me that you've got the courage to
put your differences aside because we're
family.
Don't you see? That's all that matters
now.
Forgive me.
I can't.
Then I am going to stand here in my
wedding dress until it rots.
in token of your covenant with one
another, give each other the right hand.
But God hath joined together.
Let no man put a thunder.
Big Miles now.
Excuse me.
Ladies and gentlemen.
You have to forgive me. I can't see
everyone.
But I know you're all here.
I'm so proud to be part of the King
family.
Finest people I know.
Took me in like a son.
Helped me like one of their own.
And I'll be grateful to the end of my
days.
Thank you all for calling.
And now, speaking on behalf of the
family, I'd like to introduce Miss
King.
Ladies
and
gentlemen, today, on this day of days...
the most courageous young woman came to
visit me.
And I learned something valuable from
her.
You see, I'd been fretting and fuming
over the changes sweeping over our
town, and change is inevitable.
Of course it is.
People will leave our town.
Some may have to.
But Avonlea will never vanish.
Gus and Felicity will be staying here to
carry on with the foundling home and to
one day start a family of their own,
perhaps.
But wherever they go, all the young
people of Avonlea, the memory of this
the people, the land, the sea, these
things will never be
forgotten, but will remain in their
hearts forever.
And so I'll...
I'll ask you all now to raise your
glasses and join me in a toast to the
bride and groom.
Bride and groom.
Then, then, loved one, near and afar,
that
wherever you wander, wherever glorious
adventures lie ahead of you, you can
easy knowing you've a place to come home
to.
The dearest spot on earth.
Our Avonlea.
To Avonlea. Avonlea.